hello everyone this is Frank defreitis
welcome to a new season of holotalk to
start this season off I am in Montreal
Canada and I am at the holography studio
of hollow storm we're going to be
speaking with Bruno Lavina today who
runs the lab here and he's going to be
able to tell you a little bit more
specifically about what he does here and
what they're doing here with Hollister
how you doing Bruno fine this is a great
town I have to tell you I've been doing
a lot of traveling lately and there are
some other towns that you know I like a
lot but Montreal just uh it's it's
vibrant there's a lot going on it has a
lot of snap to it which a lot of cities
do but the difference with Montreal is
the fact that at the same time there's
something that's just very laid back
about it you know it's it's a it's a
nice feeling because usually you have
one or the other you're in a town where
it's so boring that you're falling
asleep or a town where it's so hectic
that you just feel like your nerves are
on edge but uh
this sort of like has this beautiful
balance here and I had a chance to go up
into your Mountain Area up at Mom
treblanc and staying in love all and
back down here in Montreal today so it's
good to have you on the show and uh why
don't you start off by telling us a
little bit about the whole star uh I
understand it was probably here before
you got here so if you know any early
history about it maybe we could start
out with that uh um well olustar was uh
was a project uh of Eric Moscow at the
time uh our first year was in 1988
and and uh student here wanted to build
a lab a nonography lab so everything we
got here uh it's because of them so
we're really grateful of them
and
uh years years after years that they
have been putting some equipment in the
lab so right now we're we're pretty
pretty well equipped and um
you know about is there is about history
it's about that uh olustar is first of
all a student lab uh build by student
for students so we keep we keep the
prices low and everything is that with
some student I won't even attempt the
name of the college maybe you could tell
everyone the name of the college I'm
having a hard enough time at the street
signs it's a beautiful language but I
just you know coming from Philadelphia
in the way I talk you know just forget
about it yeah it's a college
College the Mason off
well we're going to have a couple
pictures of the lab on the website and
there will also be a link to go back to
the holostar website so that when you're
listening to hollow talk if you call the
holotalk webpage back up you'll see that
link there click on the link and it'll
take you over to holostar so instead of
just you know sitting there listening to
the interview you can actually do a
little bit of a tour
so this is a learning that what is it
that students are learning here do you
approach holography from an artistic
standpoint or do you approach it from a
scientific technical standpoint here at
the college first of all when we have a
student here they have to to get their
inscription done
after that we we do both sides we start
with a narcissistic approach and when we
have students that are interested in the
optical side and scientific side you
know we we just
to learn more and more now do they get
credits college credits for taking this
course nope not at all this is just
totally elective that they would come in
and work with it exactly
exactly how is this tied into the
college is this is this a business is
this what is this uh we have a status
that is a bit weird because at the same
time we are there for the student as an
uh Workshop as a workshop uh like uh
other Workshop in in the
uh like photography and music or
everything like that but at the same
time we're a resource for our uh
artists in Montreal and in Canada
because there's no there there's not
really much labs in Canada
there used to be uh other labs in
Montreal but they're gone now
uh what what happened in Montreal the
holography I was here 15 years ago the
Old Port for uh images and time and
space
it seemed like it was a very active
holography Community here at the time
what happened uh I don't really know but
I I wasn't there at the time so I'm
still young again
uh now uh starting you're trying to
start a holography community up again
right yeah we're we're trying to build a
new community here uh so it's uh it's
it's what I do with uh Nadia here which
is an artist in uh a visual artist and
installation and everything so we're
we're trying to build back the the
Montreal commune Community
but right now the fundings are really
low so we're trying to to to find some
and we have a lot of difficulty but I'm
pretty sure and in a couple of years uh
there will be uh there'll be some new
excitement in holography in Montreal is
there anyone that you can think of now
who's actively doing holography in the
Montreal area at all uh they're still
maybe you know him
uh yeah which we do contract here within
uh pretty often uh and uh well uh
Americans so
all very familiar names going back many
many years yeah
so those uh those members are still
active still active but in the last
years uh things were pretty low but
we're hoping to to to build it back
now can someone come down here and learn
about lasers as far as technology and
maybe take that learning and go to a
community college somewhere to maybe
become laser technician or something of
that nature
uh well I don't really know uh
who almost a good part of our student
here goes to uh engineering after coming
getting here uh
I I don't know
uh
a program of laser technician or
something like that when you want to
work with Optics and lasers and
everything that's around it uh right
here you have to to have an engineering
uh diploma yeah I believe in the states
they have like a
12-month certificate you can get because
every hospital that's here in Montreal
has lasers inside the hospital and
someone has to maintain the lasers so
you go to a small community college get
a laser technician certificate and
you're the person that the laser
companies hire to go
and maintain the equipment but that's
that's off the side of holography but
since you have a laser here it could be
something that could be offered anyway
yeah yeah sure yeah
um why don't you tell us a little about
projects that you've been working on
recently as far as some of the work that
you've been doing uh right now we're
doing work uh in the shadowgram with uh
Jose
and we're still doing contracts every
summer uh when when the the classes are
open for the students it's during the
semesters and
we we pretty much uh give the labs to
them during the semesters but in the
summer it's time to to get money so we
have to do contract analography and
everything uh
for for the past years where we were
working about like that and
from years to years
worked the Summers and stood with the
students in the semesters we had we have
a lot of projects like the holographic
kit and that we do that the holography
that kid that we borrowed to the to to
everyone that wants to do oligraphy tell
us a little about that that goes after
schools Educators and students as well
right there's like four kids that go out
the kids can make Holograms right yep
with this kit we we can do uh
one beam reflection and one being
transmission work uh it's not really big
but uh it's it's it's really nice
equipment to start with
for for students that sometimes are 12
years old they don't have access to that
kind of equipment so they're really
grateful to to to to be able to
milligrams in their basement have you
had an opportunity to see work of other
artists around the world and and if you
have do you feel that artists that have
worked in the field of holography in
Montreal do they have a specific style
that you feel is a little different from
what you see in other areas
I've been traveling a bit but
um never got the chance because of my
study I never got the chance to get out
of Montreal really so this summer I'm
planning to visit oral Center in New
York and maybe holographic Arts with
John Perry
uh well I'm hoping that I can try to
find the fundings to go there uh being a
student is not uh not always easy to
find the money but uh I have a lot of
Hope on that side
for the question about uh Montreal
artists
um
well I I don't feel that there's
anything really different from that
they're doing uh different from the
other parts of the world uh I know that
me and Nadia where
we're starting we hope to start a new
feeling about telegraphy uh well to to
do some something different but yeah
that's that's future
I've I've been combining holography with
some digital photography and Photoshop
work and uh doing what's I guess
considered 2D 3D type of work as well so
I guess with the computer coming in do
you find yourself doing any uh computer
manipulation of images or are you
working more from objects still uh we
still work more from objects but we have
we have linked with uh Montreal company
which will have a pretty integration of
digital work with holography
right now I can't I can't talk about it
but because I'm under NDA but there's
pretty much excitement coming uh in the
in next year now how about workshops
were just a general public if someone
John Smith or whatever his name would be
would want to come in and do some
Holograms can the public take workshops
here sure uh we just uh integrate them
with the the students it's it's that
easy
as long as your course run uh it's it's
a 12 uh 12 weeks after each semester and
we we do a lot of work with the students
shadowgram
some uh how do you put it in English
cup transmission copies okay yeah H1 H2
everything everything like that so they
they pretty much can choose what they
want to do and we do it with them
okay well Bruno is there anything you'd
like to add what can you tell us a
little I think you did tell us a little
about naughty is there anything you'd
like to add I know she is out of town
you know today and unfortunately we
didn't get a chance to get her in on a
show but maybe we could get her in over
the phone at another time to talk about
her creative work I imagine you approach
it more from the technical aspect uh
what about Nadia Let's uh uh well Nadia
uh begin here uh about one year ago uh
when she was at the University and all
right
um uh first of all when when she saw the
yellowgram she just
yeah so she came by and asked me a lot
of uh about holography and at the time I
was thinking of leaving here to to
finish my study
and
and right now I'm forming her to to to
replace me so right now we do for the
for the next year we do a semester each
of work with the students and I'm hoping
that in the future she'll get uh
she'll take just run with it yep she she
that she'll run the lab uh I'm not
teaching thinking of leaving everything
here I still want that touch I still
want to have touch with the students and
and the equipment here but uh for five
years I I left my study at University
for this yeah for this for this exactly
so I know what to talk about
so I I I need to finish this uh you need
to get on with your life
yeah that feeling comes over a lot of us
that have been working in holography
from time to time why don't you tell us
a little bit about the equipment up here
I see you've got the monster 125 up
there maybe tell us a little bit about
that and the other lasers which
sorry
uh the monster one uh it's an old laser
uh really modified the to fit our needs
uh we're still offering it
we still do a lot of work with it but
where I have a lot of work of Hope on
your driver for you Alzheimer's out
there it's a specter physics 125 which I
imagine some of the younger people in
holography wouldn't recognize because uh
definitely takes two people to lift that
baby up off the floor from what I
remember yeah and well our other laser
uh which we don't use anymore because
it's too dangerous
is another spectrophysic uh argon uh
laser uh which is 5 watts and for the
student it doesn't really fit our needs
it's just too dangerous does it still
work uh yeah it's a it still work but uh
I hate touching that kind of laser uh
but well do you burn it from time to
time just to burn it
uh not really uh I'm well I don't really
like it anyway for alligraphy it's not a
really good laser not good car events
and everything so I just leave it there
for now
uh maybe in the future we'll we'll use
it to do some really large copies but
for now we don't we don't want to use
that kind of stuff uh and or other laser
which is really nice is uh yag uh 100
and 50 milliwatts from Crystal laser and
this this one is the one I I use the
most for now but I as I said I have a
lot of Hope in your driver yeah thank
you very much what do you plan on using
for your workshops and things or taking
because you can run it off of batteries
yeah
um for now I I I we just want to replace
uh the 125 yeah the 125
we would need
a lot of work to uh get the 125 really
working well and we don't have that kind
of times armor so where we're planning
to replace replace it with the the diode
and now if you pop a diode is 35 bucks
and you're got another one exactly yeah
so yeah it'll kick the pants off that
125 too
now that I'm really excited to to to try
your driver and if if things Works uh
I'm well planning to to to get a couple
of more okay let me know so I make sure
I have them I don't even have one I
think the one I gave you was maybe one I
had yeah so it's like that uh you know
the Shoemaker that has holes in his
shoes you know because he's so busy with
everyone else's shoes okay well Bruno I
want to thank you very much for taking
the time to come on the show there's a
lot of people out there that have been
listening to this uh once again this is
in Montreal so there's a link on the
whole talk page click on that it'll take
you over to the whole store website and
if you want to drop Bruno an email tell
them hi or contact them if you happen to
be in the Montreal area and would like
to learn about holography yeah I don't
know if you can just stop in but you can
contact him and maybe he can give you
information about workshops to come in
and make a few Holograms of your own so
Bruno thank you very much